<Metabolites><creation_date>2005-11-16 15:48:42 UTC</creation_date><update_date>2020-06-15 17:04:51 UTC</update_date><accession>HMDB0000027</accession><name>Tetrahydrobiopterin</name><normal_concentrations><concentration><biospecimen>Blood</biospecimen><concentration_value>0.0110 +/- 0.0008</concentration_value><subject_age>Adult (&gt;18 years old)</subject_age><subject_sex>Both</subject_sex><subject_condition>Normal</subject_condition><references><reference><reference_text>Ueda S, Matsuoka H, Miyazaki H, Usui M, Okuda S, Imaizumi T: Tetrahydrobiopterin restores endothelial function in long-term smokers. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2000 Jan;35(1):71-5.</reference_text><pubmed_id>10636262</pubmed_id></reference></references></concentration><concentration><biospecimen>Blood</biospecimen><concentration_value>0.0093 +/- 0.0005</concentration_value><subject_age>Adult (&gt;18 years old)</subject_age><subject_sex>Both</subject_sex><subject_condition>Normal</subject_condition><references><reference><reference_text>Yada T, Kaji S, Akasaka T, Mochizuki S, Ogasawara Y, Tanemoto K, Yoshida K, Kajiya F: Changes of asymmetric dimethylarginine, nitric oxide, tetrahydrobiopterin, and oxidative stress in patients with acute myocardial infarction by medical treatments. Clin Hemorheol Microcirc. 2007;37(3):269-76.</reference_text><pubmed_id>17726257</pubmed_id></reference></references></concentration></normal_concentrations><abnormal_concentrations><concentration><biospecimen>Blood</biospecimen><concentration_value>0.16 (0.0-5.8)</concentration_value><patient_age>Adult (&gt;18 years old)</patient_age><patient_sex>Both</patient_sex><patient_information>Septic shock</patient_information><comment>Without renal failure, measured in plasma
</comment><references><reference><reference_text>Galley HF, Le Cras AE, Yassen K, Grant IS, Webster NR: Circulating tetrahydrobiopterin concentrations in patients with septic shock. Br J Anaesth. 2001 Apr;86(4):578-80.</reference_text><pubmed_id>11573638</pubmed_id></reference></references></concentration><concentration><biospecimen>Blood</biospecimen><concentration_value>1.2 (0.8-14.9)</concentration_value><patient_age>Adult (&gt;18 years old)</patient_age><patient_sex>Both</patient_sex><patient_information>Septic shock</patient_information><comment>With renal failure, measured in plasma
</comment><references><reference><reference_text>Galley HF, Le Cras AE, Yassen K, Grant IS, Webster NR: Circulating tetrahydrobiopterin concentrations in patients with septic shock. Br J Anaesth. 2001 Apr;86(4):578-80.</reference_text><pubmed_id>11573638</pubmed_id></reference></references></concentration><concentration><biospecimen>Blood</biospecimen><concentration_value>0.0099 +/- 0.0008</concentration_value><patient_age>Adult (&gt;18 years old)</patient_age><patient_sex>Both</patient_sex><patient_information>Smoking</patient_information><references><reference><reference_text>Ueda S, Matsuoka H, Miyazaki H, Usui M, Okuda S, Imaizumi T: Tetrahydrobiopterin restores endothelial function in long-term smokers. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2000 Jan;35(1):71-5.</reference_text><pubmed_id>10636262</pubmed_id></reference></references></concentration><concentration><biospecimen>Blood</biospecimen><concentration_value>0.0044 +/- 0.0007</concentration_value><patient_age>Adult (&gt;18 years old)</patient_age><patient_sex>Both</patient_sex><patient_information>Myocardial infarction</patient_information><comment>In plasma, acute myocardial infarction
</comment><references><reference><reference_text>Yada T, Kaji S, Akasaka T, Mochizuki S, Ogasawara Y, Tanemoto K, Yoshida K, Kajiya F: Changes of asymmetric dimethylarginine, nitric oxide, tetrahydrobiopterin, and oxidative stress in patients with acute myocardial infarction by medical treatments. Clin Hemorheol Microcirc. 2007;37(3):269-76.</reference_text><pubmed_id>17726257</pubmed_id></reference></references></concentration></abnormal_concentrations><diseases><disease><name>Septic shock</name><omim_id /><references><reference><reference_text>Kaufmann I, Hoelzl A, Schliephake F, Hummel T, Chouker A, Lysenko L, Peter K, Thiel M: Effects of adenosine on functions of polymorphonuclear leukocytes from patients with septic shock. Shock. 2007 Jan;27(1):25-31.</reference_text><pubmed_id>17172976</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Galley HF, Le Cras AE, Yassen K, Grant IS, Webster NR: Circulating tetrahydrobiopterin concentrations in patients with septic shock. Br J Anaesth. 2001 Apr;86(4):578-80.</reference_text><pubmed_id>11573638</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Jabs CM, Sigurdsson GH, Neglen P: Plasma levels of high-energy compounds compared with severity of illness in critically ill patients in the intensive care unit. Surgery. 1998 Jul;124(1):65-72.</reference_text><pubmed_id>9663253</pubmed_id></reference></references></disease><disease><name>Smoking</name><omim_id /><references><reference><reference_text>Ruppert T, Scherer G, Tricker AR, Adlkofer F: trans,trans-muconic acid as a biomarker of non-occupational environmental exposure to benzene. Int Arch Occup Environ Health. 1997;69(4):247-51.</reference_text><pubmed_id>9137998</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Zuccaro P, Altieri I, Rosa M, Passa AR, Pichini S, Ricciarello G, Pacifici R: Determination of nicotine and four metabolites in the serum of smokers by high-performance liquid chromatography with ultraviolet detection. J Chromatogr. 1993 Nov 24;621(2):257-61.</reference_text><pubmed_id>8294547</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Ueda S, Matsuoka H, Miyazaki H, Usui M, Okuda S, Imaizumi T: Tetrahydrobiopterin restores endothelial function in long-term smokers. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2000 Jan;35(1):71-5.</reference_text><pubmed_id>10636262</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Carmella SG, La Voie EJ, Hecht SS: Quantitative analysis of catechol and 4-methylcatechol in human urine. Food Chem Toxicol. 1982 Oct;20(5):587-90.</reference_text><pubmed_id>6890513</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Moyer TP, Charlson JR, Enger RJ, Dale LC, Ebbert JO, Schroeder DR, Hurt RD: Simultaneous analysis of nicotine, nicotine metabolites, and tobacco alkaloids in serum or urine by tandem mass spectrometry, with clinically relevant metabolic profiles. Clin Chem. 2002 Sep;48(9):1460-71.</reference_text><pubmed_id>12194923</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Chen HJ, Wu CF, Huang JL: Measurement of urinary excretion of 5-hydroxymethyluracil in human by GC/NICI/MS: correlation with cigarette smoking, urinary TBARS and etheno DNA adduct. Toxicol Lett. 2005 Mar 15;155(3):403-10.</reference_text><pubmed_id>15649624</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Massadeh AM, Gharaibeh AA, Omari KW: A single-step extraction method for the determination of nicotine and cotinine in Jordanian smokers' blood and urine samples by RP-HPLC and GC-MS. J Chromatogr Sci. 2009 Feb;47(2):170-7.</reference_text><pubmed_id>19222926</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Orhan H, Coolen S, Meerman JH: Quantification of urinary o,o'-dityrosine, a biomarker for oxidative damage to proteins, by high performance liquid chromatography with triple quadrupole tandem mass spectrometry. A comparison with ion-trap tandem mass spectrometry. J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci. 2005 Nov 15;827(1):104-8.</reference_text><pubmed_id>15878312</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Schettgen T, Musiol A, Kraus T: Simultaneous determination of mercapturic acids derived from ethylene oxide (HEMA), propylene oxide (2-HPMA), acrolein (3-HPMA), acrylamide (AAMA) and N,N-dimethylformamide (AMCC) in human urine using liquid chromatography/tandem mass spectrometry. Rapid Commun Mass Spectrom. 2008 Sep;22(17):2629-38. doi: 10.1002/rcm.3659.</reference_text><pubmed_id>18666198</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Li N, Jia X, Chen CY, Blumberg JB, Song Y, Zhang W, Zhang X, Ma G, Chen J: Almond consumption reduces oxidative DNA damage and lipid peroxidation in male smokers. J Nutr. 2007 Dec;137(12):2717-22.</reference_text><pubmed_id>18029489</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Malkawi AH, Al-Ghananeem AM, de Leon J, Crooks PA: Nicotine exposure can be detected in cerebrospinal fluid of active and passive smokers. J Pharm Biomed Anal. 2009 Jan 15;49(1):129-32. doi: 10.1016/j.jpba.2008.10.003. Epub 2008 Oct 15.</reference_text><pubmed_id>19036546</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Geigy Scientific Tables, 8th Rev edition, pp. 165-177. Edited by C. Lentner, West Cadwell, N.J.: Medical education Div., Ciba-Geigy Corp., Basel, Switzerland c1981-1992.</reference_text><pubmed_id /></reference></references></disease><disease><name>Myocardial infarction</name><omim_id /><references><reference><reference_text>Wannemacher RW Jr, Klainer AS, Dinterman RE, Beisel WR: The significance and mechanism of an increased serum phenylalanine-tyrosine ratio during infection. Am J Clin Nutr. 1976 Sep;29(9):997-1006.</reference_text><pubmed_id>822705</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Mocatta TJ, Pilbrow AP, Cameron VA, Senthilmohan R, Frampton CM, Richards AM, Winterbourn CC: Plasma concentrations of myeloperoxidase predict mortality after myocardial infarction. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2007 May 22;49(20):1993-2000. Epub 2007 May 4.</reference_text><pubmed_id>17512353</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Yada T, Kaji S, Akasaka T, Mochizuki S, Ogasawara Y, Tanemoto K, Yoshida K, Kajiya F: Changes of asymmetric dimethylarginine, nitric oxide, tetrahydrobiopterin, and oxidative stress in patients with acute myocardial infarction by medical treatments. Clin Hemorheol Microcirc. 2007;37(3):269-76.</reference_text><pubmed_id>17726257</pubmed_id></reference></references></disease><disease><name>Epilepsy</name><omim_id /><references><reference><reference_text>Rainesalo S, Keranen T, Palmio J, Peltola J, Oja SS, Saransaari P: Plasma and cerebrospinal fluid amino acids in epileptic patients. Neurochem Res. 2004 Jan;29(1):319-24.</reference_text><pubmed_id>14992292</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Cady EB, Lorek A, Penrice J, Reynolds EO, Iles RA, Burns SP, Coutts GA, Cowan FM: Detection of propan-1,2-diol in neonatal brain by in vivo proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy. Magn Reson Med. 1994 Dec;32(6):764-7.</reference_text><pubmed_id>7869898</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Perosa SR, Porcionatto MA, Cukiert A, Martins JR, Amado D, Nader HB, Cavalheiro EA, Leite JP, Naffah-Mazzacoratti MG: Extracellular matrix components are altered in the hippocampus, cortex, and cerebrospinal fluid of patients with mesial temporal lobe epilepsy. Epilepsia. 2002;43 Suppl 5:159-61.</reference_text><pubmed_id>12121313</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Spanaki MV, Siegel H, Kopylev L, Fazilat S, Dean A, Liow K, Ben-Menachem E, Gaillard WD, Theodore WH: The effect of vigabatrin (gamma-vinyl GABA) on cerebral blood flow and metabolism. Neurology. 1999 Oct 22;53(7):1518-22.</reference_text><pubmed_id>10534261</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Rating D, Siemes H, Loscher W: Low CSF GABA concentration in children with febrile convulsions, untreated epilepsy, and meningitis. J Neurol. 1983;230(4):217-25.</reference_text><pubmed_id>6198481</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Botez MI, Young SN: Effects of anticonvulsant treatment and low levels of folate and thiamine on amine metabolites in cerebrospinal fluid. Brain. 1991 Feb;114 ( Pt 1A):333-48.</reference_text><pubmed_id>1705463</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Kobayashi K, Koide Y, Yoshino K, Shohmori T: [P-hydroxyphenylacetic acid concentrations in cerebrospinal fluid]. No To Shinkei. 1982 Aug;34(8):769-74.</reference_text><pubmed_id>7126379</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Czarnecka J, Cieslak M, Michal K: Application of solid phase extraction and high-performance liquid chromatography to qualitative and quantitative analysis of nucleotides and nucleosides in human cerebrospinal fluid. J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci. 2005 Aug 5;822(1-2):85-90.</reference_text><pubmed_id>15993662</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Shaywitz BA, Cohen DJ, Bowers MB: Reduced cerebrospinal fluid 5-hydroxyindoleacetic acid and homovanillic acid in children with epilepsy. Neurology. 1975 Jan;25(1):72-9.</reference_text><pubmed_id>803305</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Anagnostouli M, Livaniou E, Nyalala JO, Evangelatos G, Zournas C, Ithakissios DS, Papageorgiou C: Cerebrospinal fluid levels of biotin in various neurological disorders. Acta Neurol Scand. 1999 Jun;99(6):387-92.</reference_text><pubmed_id>10577274</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Romigi A, Bari M, Placidi F, Marciani MG, Malaponti M, Torelli F, Izzi F, Prosperetti C, Zannino S, Corte F, Chiaramonte C, Maccarrone M: Cerebrospinal fluid levels of the endocannabinoid anandamide are reduced in patients with untreated newly diagnosed temporal lobe epilepsy. Epilepsia. 2010 May;51(5):768-72. doi: 10.1111/j.1528-1167.2009.02334.x. Epub 2009 Oct 8.</reference_text><pubmed_id>19817812</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Hirai K, Seki T: Cerebrospinal fluid somatostatin levels in febrile seizures and epilepsy in children. Neuropeptides. 2000 Feb;34(1):18-24.</reference_text><pubmed_id>10688964</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Peters JG: Dopamine, noradrenaline and serotonin spinal fluid metabolites in temporal lobe epileptic patients with schizophrenic symptomatology. Eur Neurol. 1979;18(1):15-8.</reference_text><pubmed_id>436860</pubmed_id></reference></references></disease></diseases></Metabolites>