<Metabolites><creation_date>2005-11-16 15:48:42 UTC</creation_date><update_date>2020-06-24 17:41:31 UTC</update_date><accession>HMDB0000023</accession><name>(S)-3-Hydroxyisobutyric acid</name><normal_concentrations><concentration><biospecimen>Blood</biospecimen><concentration_value>21.0 +/- 2.0</concentration_value><subject_age>Adult (&gt;18 years old)</subject_age><subject_sex>Both</subject_sex><subject_condition>Normal</subject_condition><comment>Concentration refers to racemic mixture</comment><references><reference><reference_text>Avogaro A, Bier DM: Contribution of 3-hydroxyisobutyrate to the measurement of 3-hydroxybutyrate in human plasma: comparison of enzymatic and gas-liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry assays in normal and in diabetic subjects. J Lipid Res. 1989 Nov;30(11):1811-7.</reference_text><pubmed_id>2614280</pubmed_id></reference></references></concentration><concentration><biospecimen>Blood</biospecimen><concentration_value>20.0 (4.0-48.0)</concentration_value><subject_age>Children (1-13 years old)</subject_age><subject_sex>Both</subject_sex><subject_condition>Normal</subject_condition><references><reference><reference_text>Hoffmann GF, Meier-Augenstein W, Stockler S, Surtees R, Rating D, Nyhan WL: Physiology and pathophysiology of organic acids in cerebrospinal fluid. J Inherit Metab Dis. 1993;16(4):648-69.</reference_text><pubmed_id>8412012</pubmed_id></reference></references></concentration></normal_concentrations>
<abnormal_concentrations>
<concentration><biospecimen>Blood</biospecimen><concentration_value>38.0 +/- 5.0</concentration_value><patient_age>Adult (&gt;18 years old)</patient_age><patient_sex>Both</patient_sex><patient_information>Diabetes </patient_information><comment>Concentration refers to racemic mixture
</comment><references><reference><reference_text>Avogaro A, Bier DM: Contribution of 3-hydroxyisobutyrate to the measurement of 3-hydroxybutyrate in human plasma: comparison of enzymatic and gas-liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry assays in normal and in diabetic subjects. J Lipid Res. 1989 Nov;30(11):1811-7.</reference_text><pubmed_id>2614280</pubmed_id></reference></references></concentration>
</abnormal_concentrations><diseases><disease><name>Diabetes mellitus type 2</name><omim_id>125853</omim_id><references><reference><reference_text>Tuma P, Samcova E, Balinova P: Determination of 3-methylhistidine and 1-methylhistidine in untreated urine samples by capillary electrophoresis. J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci. 2005 Jul 5;821(1):53-9.</reference_text><pubmed_id>15899597</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Costa A, Iguala I, Bedini J, Quinto L, Conget I: Uric acid concentration in subjects at risk of type 2 diabetes mellitus: relationship to components of the metabolic syndrome. Metabolism. 2002 Mar;51(3):372-5.</reference_text><pubmed_id>11887176</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Dungan KM, Buse JB, Largay J, Kelly MM, Button EA, Kato S, Wittlin S: 1,5-anhydroglucitol and postprandial hyperglycemia as measured by continuous glucose monitoring system in moderately controlled patients with diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2006 Jun;29(6):1214-9.</reference_text><pubmed_id>16731998</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Sheikh-Ali M, Karon BS, Basu A, Kudva YC, Muller LA, Xu J, Schwenk WF, Miles JM: Can serum beta-hydroxybutyrate be used to diagnose diabetic ketoacidosis? Diabetes Care. 2008 Apr;31(4):643-7. doi: 10.2337/dc07-1683. Epub 2008 Jan 9.</reference_text><pubmed_id>18184896</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Tasker RC, Lutman D, Peters MJ: Hyperventilation in severe diabetic ketoacidosis. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2005 Jul;6(4):405-11.</reference_text><pubmed_id>15982426</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Bales JR, Higham DP, Howe I, Nicholson JK, Sadler PJ: Use of high-resolution proton nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy for rapid multi-component analysis of urine. Clin Chem. 1984 Mar;30(3):426-32.</reference_text><pubmed_id>6321058</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Wahl HG, Hoffmann A, Luft D, Liebich HM: Analysis of volatile organic compounds in human urine by headspace gas chromatography-mass spectrometry with a multipurpose sampler. J Chromatogr A. 1999 Jun 25;847(1-2):117-25.</reference_text><pubmed_id>10431355</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Hoppel CL, Genuth SM: Urinary excretion of acetylcarnitine during human diabetic and fasting ketosis. Am J Physiol. 1982 Aug;243(2):E168-72.</reference_text><pubmed_id>6810706</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Zhang AQ, Mitchell SC, Smith RL: Dimethylamine in human urine. Clin Chim Acta. 1995 Jan 16;233(1-2):81-8.</reference_text><pubmed_id>7758205</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Stickle D, Turk J: A kinetic mass balance model for 1,5-anhydroglucitol: applications to monitoring of glycemic control. Am J Physiol. 1997 Oct;273(4 Pt 1):E821-30.</reference_text><pubmed_id>9357814</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>del Carmen Crespillo M, Olveira G, de Adana MS, Rojo-Martinez G, Garcia-Aleman J, Olvera P, Soriguer F, Munoz A: Metabolic effects of an enteral nutrition formula for diabetes: comparison with standard formulas in patients with type 1 diabetes. Clin Nutr. 2003 Oct;22(5):483-7.</reference_text><pubmed_id>14512036</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Blomqvist G, Alvarsson M, Grill V, Von Heijne G, Ingvar M, Thorell JO, Stone-Elander S, Widen L, Ekberg K: Effect of acute hyperketonemia on the cerebral uptake of ketone bodies in nondiabetic subjects and IDDM patients. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2002 Jul;283(1):E20-8.</reference_text><pubmed_id>12067838</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Stupar J, Vrtovec M, Dolinsek F: Longitudinal hair chromium profiles of elderly subjects with normal glucose tolerance and type 2 diabetes mellitus. Metabolism. 2007 Jan;56(1):94-104.</reference_text><pubmed_id>17161231</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Shin CS, Moon BS, Park KS, Kim SY, Park SJ, Chung MH, Lee HK: Serum 8-hydroxy-guanine levels are increased in diabetic patients. Diabetes Care. 2001 Apr;24(4):733-7.</reference_text><pubmed_id>11315839</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Nguyen TM, Rodriguez LM, Mason KJ, Heptulla RA: Serum 1,5-anhydroglucitol (Glycomark) levels in children with and without type 1 diabetes mellitus. Pediatr Diabetes. 2007 Aug;8(4):214-9.</reference_text><pubmed_id>17659063</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Guevara-Aguirre J, Guevara-Aguirre M, Saavedra J, Bernstein G, Rosenbloom AL: Comparison of oral insulin spray and subcutaneous regular insulin at mealtime in type 1 diabetes. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2007 Aug;9(4):372-6.</reference_text><pubmed_id>17705693</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>McLellan AC, Phillips SA, Thornalley PJ: Fluorimetric assay of D-lactate. Anal Biochem. 1992 Oct;206(1):12-6.</reference_text><pubmed_id>1456422</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Giussi GA, Ballejo G, Benedetti WL: Estriol serum levels, neonatal vitality and stromal villous edema in diabetic pregnancies. Acta Diabetol Lat. 1979 Apr-Jun;16(2):105-10.</reference_text><pubmed_id>484160</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Ostlund RE Jr, McGill JB, Herskowitz I, Kipnis DM, Santiago JV, Sherman WR: D-chiro-inositol metabolism in diabetes mellitus. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1993 Nov 1;90(21):9988-92.</reference_text><pubmed_id>8234346</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Greco AV, Mingrone G, Capristo E, Benedetti G, De Gaetano A, Gasbarrini G: The metabolic effect of dodecanedioic acid infusion in non-insulin-dependent diabetic patients. Nutrition. 1998 Apr;14(4):351-7.</reference_text><pubmed_id>9591306</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Mine S, Okada Y, Kawahara C, Tabata T, Tanaka Y: Serum hyaluronan concentration as a marker of angiopathy in patients with diabetes mellitus. Endocr J. 2006 Dec;53(6):761-6. Epub 2006 Sep 12.</reference_text><pubmed_id>16966827</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Liebich HM, Buelow HJ, Kallmayer R: Quantification of endogenous aliphatic alcohols in serum and urine. J Chromatogr. 1982 Apr 30;239:343-9.</reference_text><pubmed_id>7096503</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Avogaro A, Bier DM: Contribution of 3-hydroxyisobutyrate to the measurement of 3-hydroxybutyrate in human plasma: comparison of enzymatic and gas-liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry assays in normal and in diabetic subjects. J Lipid Res. 1989 Nov;30(11):1811-7.</reference_text><pubmed_id>2614280</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Khuhawar MY, Zardari LA, Laghari AJ: Capillary gas chromatographic determination of methylglyoxal from serum of diabetic patients by precolumn derivatization with 1,2-diamonopropane. J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci. 2008 Sep 15;873(1):15-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jchromb.2008.04.048. Epub 2008 May 17.</reference_text><pubmed_id>18760976</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Kawasaki T, Akanuma H, Yamanouchi T: Increased fructose concentrations in blood and urine in patients with diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2002 Feb;25(2):353-7.</reference_text><pubmed_id>11815509</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Noroozi M, Burns J, Crozier A, Kelly IE, Lean ME: Prediction of dietary flavonol consumption from fasting plasma concentration or urinary excretion. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2000 Feb;54(2):143-9.</reference_text><pubmed_id>10694785</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Paroni R, Ceriotti F, Galanello R, Battista Leoni G, Panico A, Scurati E, Paleari R, Chemello L, Quaino V, Scaldaferri L, Lapolla A, Mosca A: Performance characteristics and clinical utility of an enzymatic method for the measurement of glycated albumin in plasma. Clin Biochem. 2007 Dec;40(18):1398-405. Epub 2007 Aug 10.</reference_text><pubmed_id>17919531</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Salek RM, Maguire ML, Bentley E, Rubtsov DV, Hough T, Cheeseman M, Nunez D, Sweatman BC, Haselden JN, Cox RD, Connor SC, Griffin JL: A metabolomic comparison of urinary changes in type 2 diabetes in mouse, rat, and human. Physiol Genomics. 2007 Apr 24;29(2):99-108. Epub 2006 Dec 26.</reference_text><pubmed_id>17190852</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Galli E, Marchini M, Saba A, Berti S, Tonacchera M, Vitti P, Scanlan TS, Iervasi G, Zucchi R: Detection of 3-iodothyronamine in human patients: a preliminary study. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2012 Jan;97(1):E69-74. doi: 10.1210/jc.2011-1115. Epub 2011 Oct 26.</reference_text><pubmed_id>22031514</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Llorach R, Urpi-Sarda M, Tulipani S, Garcia-Aloy M, Monagas M, Andres-Lacueva C: Metabolomic fingerprint in patients at high risk of cardiovascular disease by cocoa intervention. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2013 Jun;57(6):962-73. doi: 10.1002/mnfr.201200736. Epub 2013  May 2.</reference_text><pubmed_id>23637065</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>World Health Organisation Department of Noncommunicable Disease Surveillance (1999). "Definition, Diagnosis and Classification of Diabetes Mellitus and its Complications"</reference_text><pubmed_id /></reference><reference><reference_text>Rosa Va &#769;zquez-Fresno et al. An NMR metabolomics approach reveals a combined-biomarkers model in a wine interventional trial with validation in free-living individuals of the PREDIMED study.  Metabolomics (2015) 11:797- 806: https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007/s11306-014-0735-x.pdf</reference_text></reference></references></disease><disease><name>Colorectal cancer</name><omim_id>114500</omim_id><references><reference><reference_text>Ishiwata S, Itoh K, Yamaguchi T, Ishida N, Mizugaki M: Comparison of serum and urinary levels of modified nucleoside, 1-methyladenosine, in cancer patients using a monoclonal antibody-based inhibition ELISA. Tohoku J Exp Med. 1995 May;176(1):61-8.</reference_text><pubmed_id>7482520</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Monleon D, Morales JM, Barrasa A, Lopez JA, Vazquez C, Celda B: Metabolite profiling of fecal water extracts from human colorectal cancer. NMR Biomed. 2009 Apr;22(3):342-8. doi: 10.1002/nbm.1345.</reference_text><pubmed_id>19006102</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Weir TL, Manter DK, Sheflin AM, Barnett BA, Heuberger AL, Ryan EP: Stool microbiome and metabolome differences between colorectal cancer patients and healthy adults. PLoS One. 2013 Aug 6;8(8):e70803. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0070803. Print 2013.</reference_text><pubmed_id>23940645</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Phua LC, Chue XP, Koh PK, Cheah PY, Ho HK, Chan EC: Non-invasive fecal metabonomic detection of colorectal cancer. Cancer Biol Ther. 2014 Apr;15(4):389-97. doi: 10.4161/cbt.27625. Epub 2014 Jan 14.</reference_text><pubmed_id>24424155</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Ritchie SA, Ahiahonu PW, Jayasinghe D, Heath D, Liu J, Lu Y, Jin W, Kavianpour A, Yamazaki Y, Khan AM, Hossain M, Su-Myat KK, Wood PL, Krenitsky K, Takemasa I, Miyake M, Sekimoto M, Monden M, Matsubara H, Nomura F, Goodenowe DB: Reduced levels of hydroxylated, polyunsaturated ultra long-chain fatty acids in the serum of colorectal cancer patients: implications for early screening and detection. BMC Med. 2010 Feb 15;8:13. doi: 10.1186/1741-7015-8-13.</reference_text><pubmed_id>20156336</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Qiu Y, Cai G, Su M, Chen T, Zheng X, Xu Y, Ni Y, Zhao A, Xu LX, Cai S, Jia W: Serum metabolite profiling of human colorectal cancer using GC-TOFMS and UPLC-QTOFMS. J Proteome Res. 2009 Oct;8(10):4844-50. doi: 10.1021/pr9004162.</reference_text><pubmed_id>19678709</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Cheng Y, Xie G, Chen T, Qiu Y, Zou X, Zheng M, Tan B, Feng B, Dong T, He P, Zhao L, Zhao A, Xu LX, Zhang Y, Jia W: Distinct urinary metabolic profile of human colorectal cancer. J Proteome Res. 2012 Feb 3;11(2):1354-63. doi: 10.1021/pr201001a. Epub 2011 Dec 28.</reference_text><pubmed_id>22148915</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Ni Y, Xie G, Jia W: Metabonomics of human colorectal cancer: new approaches for early diagnosis and biomarker discovery. J Proteome Res. 2014 Sep 5;13(9):3857-70. doi: 10.1021/pr500443c. Epub 2014 Aug 14.</reference_text><pubmed_id>25105552</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Ikeda A, Nishiumi S, Shinohara M, Yoshie T, Hatano N, Okuno T, Bamba T, Fukusaki E, Takenawa T, Azuma T, Yoshida M: Serum metabolomics as a novel diagnostic approach for gastrointestinal cancer. Biomed Chromatogr. 2012 May;26(5):548-58. doi: 10.1002/bmc.1671. Epub 2011 Jul 20.</reference_text><pubmed_id>21773981</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Goedert JJ, Sampson JN, Moore SC, Xiao Q, Xiong X, Hayes RB, Ahn J, Shi J, Sinha R: Fecal metabolomics: assay performance and association with colorectal cancer. Carcinogenesis. 2014 Sep;35(9):2089-96. doi: 10.1093/carcin/bgu131. Epub 2014 Jul 18.</reference_text><pubmed_id>25037050</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Sinha R, Ahn J, Sampson JN, Shi J, Yu G, Xiong X, Hayes RB, Goedert JJ: Fecal Microbiota, Fecal Metabolome, and Colorectal Cancer Interrelations. PLoS One. 2016 Mar 25;11(3):e0152126. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0152126. eCollection 2016.</reference_text><pubmed_id>27015276</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Lin Y, Ma C, Liu C, Wang Z, Yang J, Liu X, Shen Z, Wu R: NMR-based fecal metabolomics fingerprinting as predictors of earlier diagnosis in patients with colorectal cancer. Oncotarget. 2016 May 17;7(20):29454-64. doi: 10.18632/oncotarget.8762.</reference_text><pubmed_id>27107423</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Brown DG, Rao S, Weir TL, O'Malia J, Bazan M, Brown RJ, Ryan EP: Metabolomics and metabolic pathway networks from human colorectal cancers, adjacent mucosa, and stool. Cancer Metab. 2016 Jun 6;4:11. doi: 10.1186/s40170-016-0151-y. eCollection 2016.</reference_text><pubmed_id>27275383</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Wang X, Wang J, Rao B, Deng L: Gut flora profiling and fecal metabolite composition of colorectal cancer patients and healthy individuals. Exp Ther Med. 2017 Jun;13(6):2848-2854. doi: 10.3892/etm.2017.4367. Epub 2017 Apr 20.</reference_text><pubmed_id>28587349</pubmed_id></reference><reference><reference_text>Silke Matysik, Caroline Ivanne Le Roy, Gerhard Liebisch, Sandrine Paule Claus. Metabolomics of fecal samples: A practical consideration. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology. Vol. 57, Part B, Nov. 2016, p.244-255: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0924224416301984</reference_text></reference></references></disease><disease><name>3-Hydroxyisobutyric aciduria</name><omim_id>236795</omim_id><references><reference><reference_text>MetaGene: Metabolic &amp; Genetic Information Center (MIC: http://www.metagene.de)</reference_text><pubmed_id /></reference></references></disease><disease><name>Eosinophilic esophagitis</name><omim_id>610247</omim_id><references><reference><reference_text>Mordechai, Hien, and David S. Wishart</reference_text><pubmed_id /></reference></references></disease></diseases></Metabolites>
